[Music]
welcome back to reality asserts itself
i'm paul jay and this is the real news
network
we're continuing our series of
interviews with john kiriakou we're at
his house as i've said before he's
continues to be under
house arrest as we do these interviews
john was the first cia officer
to officially confirm that there was in
fact a waterboarding torture program
he's also the only person that went to
jail for anything to do with a water
boarding torture program
and that was because he was the first
person to officially confirm
there was a waterboarding torture
program unfortunately the people who
were actually
doing the waterboarding and ordering the
waterboarding
aren't didn't go to jail and never kept
him any company in jail
thanks for joining us thanks for having
me so let's pick up our story from
that why did the cia target you the cia
never forgave me for confirming that
it was waterboarding and otherwise
torturing prisoners that
that torture was official u.s government
policy
and that the policy was approved by the
president never forgave me where did you
say this
and how did you get to it i said this in
december of 2007
on abc news and it it started
uh oddly for me
i got a call from brian ross let me just
back up one sec
because we've been kind of doing your
story chronologically now we're kind of
jumping
okay so if i understand correctly you
left the cia in one year 2004
2004 and you did some consulting you did
consulting for abc
and that not yet i i left the ci in 2004
and i joined deloitte and touche which
is one of the big four
uh public accounting firms okay so first
of all why did you leave the cia
i left the cia as funny as it might
sound to spend more time with my
children i had
gone through a very acrimonious divorce
my ex-wife had moved
to northeastern ohio with my two sons
so that she could be closer to her
parents and i knew that
my career was going to take me back
overseas again in short order and to
some place
not family friendly iraq afghanistan
pakistan yemen something like that
and so i decided i had had enough and
i had a friend who had a friend
at deloitte touch one of the big four
accounting firms they were looking for
someone to
head um counter not counter intelligence
but
competitive intelligence in their
washington dc office
and uh i applied for the job
and uh a couple of weeks later was made
an offer i resigned from the cia and
the very next day went into deloitte
touch why does deloitte tuschwan a cia
guy
well i was actually the fourth cia guy
that deloitte and touch
had hired they had created this this
group called the competitive
intelligence group
with the idea being that they would hire
former cia officers or other people with
experience
in intelligence collection and they
would pair those people
with the analysts the corporate uh
research analysts
to collect and analyze intelligence on
their competitors
so my job was to
collect first person human source
intelligence on
ernst and young kpmg
pricewaterhousecoopers and a myriad of
uh
consulting firms like ibm and accenture
and others
and we would collect this information
sometimes they were tips
for example well for example we tried to
to steal their
pricing models or how they determine
discounts
or interestingly at least to me
we tried to figure out which of their
partners were disgruntled
so we could steal them provided that
they were top producers and i i'm
assuming they're all doing it back to
deloitte too
absolutely to each other they all have
the same groups now i will say that
deloitte no longer exists
uh it went away during the recession but
the other the other consulting firms yes
they do have similar groups and and
they're looking are they looking for
dirt on
individuals or this is more about
recruitment it's it's much more about
recruitment and
it's it's also about undercutting
pricing if you're going to go into
to a bid with a with a price of 24
million dollars let's say
we want to know that so we can go in
with a bit of 20 million dollars
and and win the win the the job because
a 20 million dollar contract of course
is better than a zero
dollar contract and and so they're all
doing it to each other they're all so
every
this is a lot about the bidding process
then trying to get someone to spill the
beans on a bit yes the bidding process
recruiting a double agent yeah it's the
bidding process
it's discounts uh it's disgruntled
partners like i said
it's plans to expand um service lines or
offerings
anything that might give you a corporate
leg up
and were you successful wildly in some
cases really
all right that's we'll do that another
day uh
okay so then what deloitte touch
what point do you start uh consulting
for abc uh not until after i went on tv
and talked about torture
uh i was at i was at my desk at deloitte
one day and i got a call from
brian ross at abc news and brian ross
told me
that he had a source who said that i had
tortured abu zubaydah
i said that was absolutely untrue that i
was the only person who was ever kind to
abu zubaydah
and i said i never have laid a hand on
anybody least of all abu zubaydah
and he said and i learned later that
this was an old reporter's trick
he said well you can come on the show
and defend yourself in the meantime
that same day the day before
the same week whatever it was president
bush was telling the press that we do
not torture we do not torture we do not
torture
this government does not torture people
you know we we we we stick to u.s law
and
our international obligations
thirdly there are highly trained
professionals
questioning these uh extremists and
terrorists
notice we got professionals who are
trained in this uh
kind of work to get information that
will protect the american people and by
the way
we have gotten information from these
high-value detainees
that have helped protect you i knew that
was a lie
and then later he said that we don't
torture but
if there is torture it's the result of a
rogue cia officer
or a rogue operation i knew that was a
lie
so i went on abc news and
he never even asked me on camera if i
had tortured i was a beta
he just went straight into the torture
and at the time i've i felt that
waterboarding was something that we
needed to do
and as time has passed and has as
september 11th has
has you know has moved farther and
farther back into history um i think
i've changed my mind
and i think that waterboarding is
probably something that we shouldn't be
in the business of doing
why do you say that now because we're
americans and we're better than that
but at the time you didn't feel that way
at the time i was so angry
and i wanted so much to help disrupt
future attacks on the united states
that i felt it was the only thing we
could do and with zebedee you think that
was successful
it was and we have reported that khalid
sheikh muhammad
was also waterboarded i was out of it by
then but it's my understanding that he
was that he was also water but those
were really the only two
to the best of my knowledge yes and
bottom line is to sit here now do you
think that was worth it
yes did it compromise american
principles or to save american lives or
both
it i think both it may have compromised
our principles at least in the short
term
and i think it's good that we're having
a national debate about this we should
be debating this
and congress should be talking about it
because i think as a country we have to
decide if this is something that we want
to do as a matter of policy
i'm not saying now that we should but at
the very least we should be talking
about it
it shouldn't be secret it should be out
there as part of the national debate
in that interview i essentially called
the president of the united states a
liar
in fact the next day at a press
conference i am saying that the united
states does not torture the president
has been if what was done in this case
was not
torture in your opinion i'm saying the
united states does not torture well you
have a former cia officer john
kirkown now saying that waterboarding
was used since you're saying
the interrogations were legal he's
saying on the record now waterboarding
was used
in at least one case you're saying
waterboarding
is legal and i'm saying i'm not
commenting on any specific technique
i'm not commenting on that gentleman's
characteristics of
any possible technique i've given you a
very general statement
about interrogations being legal uh
limited
and is not legal within the legal
framework
yes every day so water boarding is legal
i'm not commenting on any specific
techniques and you can ask me all sorts
of different ways and we can go back and
forth but i'm not going to do it then
well immediately the cia filed what's
called a crimes report
with the justice department alleging
that i had violated my secrecy agreement
by
leaking classified information the fbi
investigated they watched the tape and
they concluded that
it was already common knowledge that we
were torturing prisoners
human rights watch had come out with a
report amnesty international had come
out with a report
so i had added nothing technically to
the debate but what i had done
was i had become the first
cia officer current or former to
actually confirm that we were torturing
prisoners and that torture was our
policy
now when you first talked about it you
defend torture do you not is that
there's a point where you say
he's been torturing a waterboard a lot
of people think that i
i was defending it in fact i was trying
to be
nuanced and i failed at being nuanced i
was trying to present it as two
questions two separate issues one
did it work and two was it right and i
said it wasn't right
it was wrong morally and ethically it
was torture and that i was opposed to it
in fact i had been asked by a senior
officer in the counter-terrorism center
if i wanted to be certified in the use
of these
so-called enhanced interrogation
techniques and i declined i said i had a
moral problem with it
on that first question did it work the
cia
officers in the field who were torturing
prisoners were reporting back
that it was working and that abu
zubaydah for example had cracked
after one session one waterboarding
session and that he had given up
actionable information that saved
american lives and that's what
when when you're on television that's
what you need at that time that's what i
knew with that
you conclude that it was done once and
it worked correct
although it was wrong it had worked we
didn't know
nobody knew until the cia inspector
general
report was released in april of 2009
that said that no he was waterboarded 83
times and khalid sheikh muhammad was
worded
waterboarded 147 times so they were even
lying
to each other internally to try to
justify this thing
so i i told brian ross what i thought
i knew as facts but i was i was wrong
so what what's the next big beat for you
when is it the inspector general's
report well yeah um
in that year 2008 to early 2009
i ended up consulting for abc news and
frankly what i had done is i called
brian ross and i said you ruined my life
the least you could do is throw me a
little bit of work and so abc brought me
on as a consultant
in early 2009 john kerry offered me a
job as the senior investigator on the
senate foreign relations committee
so i was under the impression that he
actually wanted me to investigate things
and i ran into even more trouble with
the cia
in that job now between going on tv and
acknowledging that there is torture
they open a file on you um
and and the inspector general's report
and
kerry's job how actively are they
pursuing you and how aware are you of it
i was unaware of any
investigation aimed at me
targeting me it turned out that they
never stopped investigating me from
december of 2007
until my arrest in 2012. prior to you
going on television
was there any sense that cia
wasn't happy with you oh no none on the
contrary
when i was at deloitte and touch they
were preparing to bid
for a job in the cia's counterterrorism
center i still had an active security
clearance at the time
and so they asked if they could add me
to the list of cleared individuals that
that might
participate in this contract i said yes
and i called the security officer at the
counterterrorism center
and she said yeah that's great with us
um and i ended up not doing it because
my boss was
willing to give me up for six weeks but
they wanted me for six months until the
contract really got going but i had no
problems whatsoever with the cia
intelligence because you'd think you'd
think
if they had no issues with you and you
say this one thing on tv
they would say oh look this guy's been a
stellar agent all this time and never
and so on you know and everyone already
knows it's happening
we could just like ignore it right like
by targeting you they're making it a
hundred times more an issue
even in the public eye eventually it's
gonna go public
i mean look where it's led to all these
interviews well that's why i maintain
the cia
uh is the organization that made me a
human rights activist
it's the cia that's made me uh uh
want to you know take to the streets to
defend our civil liberties
otherwise i wouldn't have given it two
minutes of thought
but you're exactly right and even if
they were angry
there are other cases of cia officers
current cia officers
exposing classified information and what
happens to them is they get a letter in
their file and they don't get promoted
for a year
they don't get seven felony charges or
five felonies
so i go back to my first question why
target you in this way
i think that the targeting came from
inside
the counterterrorism center it wasn't
necessarily the cia
as a an organization as a whole it was
ctc
ctc was run by cowboys and
and hard asses and i think that they
were so
furious that what i had done was
unforgivable
uh that that they are the ones who asked
the justice department to go after me
ctc
is this thing we see on this tv show 24
right that's
i mean does it bear any resemblance to
reality the 24
room no the room no
no that's all hollywood the the uh okay
so let's jump ahead the inspector
general's report comes out you find out
that it wasn't once it was 83 times
right and in fact the intelligence
wasn't actionable
so what does that do to you and what are
you doing well it makes me look like a
fool
at the time i was working for john kerry
i had only been there about a month
maybe six weeks but it made me look like
a fool
but i issued a statement saying i gave
the facts
as i knew them i think that the
inspector general's report shows that
the cia will lie to its own staff
officers
um i had no regrets
two years had gone by so why does this
eventually lead to a charge i don't get
i mean
how much while i was at the uh
senate foreign relations committee i
decided to do some real
investigations so
at first i wanted to investigate what
was called the dash delete massacre
this was an incident in in northern
afghanistan
on november 30th and december 1st of
where the northern alliance had captured
as many as 2
000 taliban soldiers and
wanted to incarcerate them well there
were no jails in
afghanistan big enough to hold two
thousand prisoners all at once
so what the northern alliance decided to
do was to load these men
onto container trucks and take them out
into the desert
deep into the desert and just hold them
there until they could figure out how to
get them to different jails around
themselves
this is general dostum and his men who's
now a vice president
vice president or deputy prime minister
one or the other
uh so nobody had
put any air holes in these containers
and there was no food and there was no
water
so after an eight hour drive into the
desert how many people are packed in a
container
two thousand two thousand people in a
series of containers
so after eight hours drive into the
desert one of the witnesses who survived
told us that when they opened the back
of the trucks
that bodies fell out like sardines out
of a can
so almost everybody died by our account
there were 18 survivors out of 2000. the
reason i was interested in this
is because i had taken a call from a
human rights activist who told us
that he had a witness who was a boy at
the time
and didn't go onto the truck and he said
that the boy saw
two white men wearing jeans and black
t-shirts and speaking english
at the box up well who's going to be in
mazari sharif
afghanistan speaking english wearing
blue jeans
on november 30th 2001
so i interviewed everybody at the state
department at the time who mattered
from 2001 i interviewed several human
rights activists
and i sent a letter to the agency
asking for some clarification within a
couple of days
the uh deputy office director or staff
director is what he
he's called at the senate foreign
relations committee told me that the
that the investigation was dead and to
drop it
just just quickly just coincidentally i
happened to have made a
documentary called return to kandahar in
afghanistan in the spring of 2002
and we interviewed general doston so
here's a few seconds of that just to
give you a sense of who
who who we're talking about
foreign
[Music]
in the 90s when these guys fought each
other over a million people died and
half of the city of kabul was destroyed
that's not a football game
so that's general dustin now general
dustin clearly is a
is was is a war criminal you had
uncovered
evidence that proved it and it gets shut
down
why i think that i was
poking the hornet's nest at the time and
i'm not sure if i was doing it
subconsciously or if it just worked out
that way but i wanted to know if cia
officers were present at the box up now
i know cia officers were present 20
miles away
because the box up was the same day as
the uprising
at khalati jangvi where uh
was was killed in in the taliban al
qaeda uprising that took place in that
prison
so i know they were in the area i wanted
to know what this was another slaughter
it was another slaughter yes so i
dropped that investigation
and then i got a call from a reporter
who told me that he had some information
that seemed to indicate
that the cia was taking its torturers
and putting them under state department
cover let's back up on set just to
close the loop on the previous story if
you had in fact
found that there were cia at the box up
they would have been
implicated in a war crime correct
correct
and that war crime would have been
detailed in an official report from the
senate
foreign relations committee okay
so i moved on to another investigation a
reporter called me
and said that he had information that
the cia was taking some of its torturers
and placing them under state department
cover which was a violation
of the cover agreement between the cia
and the state department
so i sent the state department a letter
asking for clarification
weeks passed something like five six
weeks passed
and finally a colleague of mine comes
into my office and says
oh you got a response to your letter
from the agency
i said i didn't get any response he said
well they classified it top secret and
you're not cleared for it i said well
what'd they say
and he smiles and he says they said go
[__] yourself
so that was the end of that
investigation so how long after all this
do you get charged
well it was another uh three years there
were other investigations too
at which i was poking them uh they even
called my wife
into the cia security office and
threatened her no your wife
my wife was a cia officer his or her was
was was
that you met at the cio we met at the
cia so they called her in and what
well i had written an op-ed in the los
angeles times in which i said that
we need to be very cautious about
iran's inroads into latin america we
need to improve our relations with
latin american countries because the
iranians are improving theirs
and i wrote one sentence
in that in that op-ed
dealing with iranian travel to latin
america now i got that
op-ed cleared by the cia so
finally they call my wife into security
and they have a camera on and
the security guy says this is not an
investigation it's an inquiry but we're
going to
tape it what do you think should be done
with people who leak classified
information
totally loaded question she said what
are you talking about
well your husband wrote an op-ed in the
los angeles times
and she said he got that op-ed cleared
let me ask
why would you have to get it cleared
you're no longer working i have to get
anything i write dealing with
intelligence cia
foreign affairs government anything for
the rest of my life
cleared by the cia's publications review
board what about this interview
or the other interviews you've been
getting well these are written written
products uh articles books magazine
articles you know op-eds interviews are
okay
interviews are okay all right go on so
she said well he got that cleared by the
publication's review board
and the the guy tells her and we really
appreciate that
but there's a line in there that is
top secret and she said well that's
impossible my husband doesn't have
access to top secret information
and he says but you do so she said
i think i've said enough and she got up
and walked to walked away
what was the line it was that iranians
no longer need visas to travel
to bolivia what so
she was top secret she was very upset
and she called me and i told her take it
easy i said do you know where i got
that information and she said no i said
i got it from the bolivian foreign
ministry's website
it's on the website and why on earth
would it be secret anyway
i told her one thing that you may want
to tell them
is number one apparently nobody in the
cia speaks spanish
first of all secondly they apparently
have a source who's selling them press
and calling it intelligence
so they were upset about that well
they're out to get you at this point at
that point they were out to get me
uh but i didn't think that this would
result in any kind of criminal
charges it's almost sounding like the
the the when you go public on the
torture issue
they open a file yeah it's this stuff
where they really decide
we have to shut this guy up well it got
much
much worse toward the end of my stay at
the senate foreign relations committee
there was an incident that i'll tell you
about part of my job was to have
okay hang on yeah this is going to be a
cliffhanger you got to join us for the
next part
to find out what happened next on
reality asserts itself
on the real news network thanks for
joining us
[Music]
you